In Indianapolis, general manager and
executive vice president Nick Cacerio
joins us. Nick, how's it going,
>> fellas? Good to be here. Always good to
visit with you.
>> All right, so this is our fifth combine
together. Your sixth off season because
we had no combine in 2021. But tell us
about the evolution as we are here. It
changes a little bit every year and we
notice some coaches, GMs or staffs
reduce capacity and who's attending.
How's all that working out for you,
Dick?
>> Yeah, no, it's working out great. Yeah,
I think the big thing for us, I mean,
Dimmitiko and I got in uh yesterday. Um,
so the big thing is kind of getting
ready for the interviews and really the
interpersonal component, trying to spend
time with the players on a personal
level. I think when you look across the
league, I mean, to your point, Mark,
some staffs are here, some aren't here.
A lot of it is just time and resource
allocation. Some of it has to do with
the way the scheduling is set up and
you've had a lot of turnover leaguewide
on a staff front. So they might feel
it's they're better served to kind of
stay back and kind of work on playbook
some of the staffing with the some of
the other things. So eventually
everybody's going to get the information
that they need from this place and then
you're going to have touch points with
the players whether it's here or whether
it's 30man visits or whether it's a pro
day. So it continues to evolve on a on a
you know yearly basis. So I think the
big thing for us is just try to get the
information that we need and just kind
of keep the ball moving. Um get ready
for you know the next couple months. I I
gotta say I am a little disappointed.
>> I thought you would be on team Harris
with the vest.
>> I do have So I actually have one up in
the room.
>> Yeah. No, but this is kind of a hoodie.
I've been I've been on the hoodie
program here.
>> I am on a hoodie program, too. But I
thought I'm going to break the vest out
today cuz I know
>> I like that one. I don't even think I
have that one. That's a good one.
>> Exactly. Borrow. It's a little bigger
than you're used to. Um, in your presser
and in talking with the Houston media,
you're asked numerous times about CJ and
his going forward team. People are
asking about trades and things like
that. You're fairly demonstrative about
your thoughts. What are your thoughts
about CJ going forward?
>> Yeah, I mean, he's our quarterback. Glad
he's our quarterback. I mean, all of us
have areas and things that we can
improve on individually, collectively,
as a team, and that's what the offseason
is about. So, CJ's played a lot of good
football. um he's had a positive in
influence and impact on the program. Um
there's always things that all of us can
do better. And I'm sure when we kind of
take a step back, you want to look at
what we accomplished during the year.
What are some areas that, you know, we
did well? What are some of the things
that we did well? What are some of the
areas we need to improve? And that's
what the offseason is about. It's about
improvement. You want to reflect on what
happened, but you can't spend too much
time on what happened because we kind of
have to prepare for what's in front of
us. Well, also you don't want to take
one game and say that's the whole
season, right? Because we were going
over some of the numbers of the season.
You improved greatly at the quarterback
position from 24 to 25 in so many key
statistical categories, Nick. Even over
23 in some cases like sack percentage,
interception rate, all those things.
>> You said it, Mark. And honestly, we
probably after about four weeks from
that point on, you know, we played
pretty good football offensively and
played pretty good football as a team
and we won nine games or 10 games in a
row, whatever it was. So, I think the
big thing is, all right, trying to
figure out what are some of the things
that we can build on and improve. I
mean, taking care of the football is of
the utmost importance, not only for us,
but when you look around the league. Um,
so that's always going to be a focus.
Um, and the quarterback's involved in
that. So whether it's Davis, whether
it's CJ, whether it's Graham Mertz or
whomever else is here, you know, playing
quarterback.
>> I think it's fascinating, Nick. You
you've done this for over two decades.
Building the team for insert year, in
this case, 2026.
When you got here in 2021, we were in a
different spot. I think everybody knows
that. And you had to go about building
the team a certain way for a few years.
And then all a sudden, we got to a
different spot. And we see kind of
evolve year-over-year. I would think
that makes the team building process for
you and do really kind of exciting like
okay where are we kind of football
existentialism where are we what are we
what do we have to do to take the next
step in 2026 is that the way you kind of
look at it and you think back to those
that first year doing our combine
interview to where we are now we're a
different program a different team a
different organization but I would think
there's probably some real fun
excitement in that for you
>> absolutely and even going back when we
first took over in 21 it might have been
different but the thought process is
very similar. So, all right, understand
where you are. What are the resources
that you have? Who are the players that
are under contract? Who are the players
that are free agents? What's the market
look like? What are our options? What's
our flexibility? I mean, this is a fun
time of year for really each team. And
it's very fluid and you have a fixed
point relative to we know the draft is
the end of April. Okay, that's that.
We're here to talk about that. But
before that, like free agency is going
to start here in a few weeks. So, we're
prepared for that. And what are the
options? understanding the markets,
understand the supply demand, understand
who's available. So, there's an element
you got to stay nimble, you got to
adjust and adapt. You got to stay
flexible and you can't get married to
one particular way of doing it. Explore
multiple options and try to figure out
what makes the most sense. And I think
the big thing is just make sure you
communicate as a staff and you're not
going to do anything kind of in a vacuum
and well, it's this group says this,
this group says that. How do we view it
as a scouting staff? How do we view as a
coaching staff? Well, how does Demo view
the player? Okay, great. Is it a fit?
Okay, great. Then we can kind of figure
out the finance the financial component
of that. Does it fit? Does it not? So,
it is it's a lot of fun. We really enjoy
it. Every day is kind of a little bit
different. You really never know what's
going to happen, but you just got to be
ready to act and then just keep pressing
forward.
>> We talked about the evolution of the
combine. What about the evolution of the
athletes you're drafting in the NIL
world coming out of college, Nick? How
are they different, if at all? Because
it affects the way I watch college
sports now. Oh, yeah. These guys are
getting paid and some of them getting
paid a lot of money. How does it affect
them as you look at them?
>> Yeah, it's just look, we're in a
different era. I mean, everybody
understands that. And again, our job is
not to be judgmental. Our job is just to
understand the situation, understand the
circumstances, understand the individual
player and the rationale behind the
decisions that they're making.
Obviously, it's a positive for some
players because they get to play more
football. So, that means you can
evaluate more snaps. They might be more
prepared to transition. You're looking
at some players started 40, 50, even 60
games. So, they're going to be prepared
for the rigors of what they're going to
have to endure. It doesn't mean they're
going to be like the perfect player, but
they might be further along in their
development than they would have been
otherwise if they didn't have this
opportunity. So, every player is a
little bit different. Every situation is
a little bit different. I mean, the
money's the money. I mean, some players
are making more money than others, just
like some players are making more money
in our league than others as well. So,
>> it's just kind of a microcosm of what's
going on at at our level. And one of the
things that is happening, and the
numbers bear this out, is in large part
because of the NIL and because of
transfer portal, there aren't as many
underassmen declaring for the draft. And
I know you guys track the underassman as
you go. But does that change anything
for you guys that you're not having as
many underassmen because I know you come
here and we talked about this before,
you come to Indie, a lot of times it's
the first time you get a chance to talk
to some of the underassman you haven't
had a chance to. Do you still kind of go
the same route even though there are
less of them?
>> For sure. And this comes back to basic
economics. It's about supply and demand.
So we've gone from 125, 130 to 6570. So
the pool has been cut in half. So okay,
>> who are the players? Who's available?
What are our options? Understanding that
pool of players. You know, we're going
to pro we've probably talked to we'll
have talked to 250 300 players between
allstar game combine visits. Doesn't
mean we're going to draft all those
players. We're probably going to pair
that down into a workable number. where
it says, "Okay, these are the players
that kind of fit the profile of the
Houston Texans." So, that's kind of how
we go about that that process.
>> Nick, what can you share with us about
how the medical process works? Because
we know Texans medical personnel are on
hand giving physicals to the players.
So, these guys have to go through a lot
of physicals. Is that limited to a
certain amount of teams? How does all
that work?
>> Yeah. So, every team has a
representative from their medical side.
So, all the team doctors are here. So I
mean I think they distribute their
responsibilities. Some players go to
this group, some but everybody gets the
same information. So the benefit is it's
all centrally located. So all the
players have to go through whatever the
medical process is. So you kind of get a
medical report. Some of this you may
know about the player, what their
condition is. Maybe it's better, maybe
it's worse. Okay? Or a player pops up
with an injury they didn't even know he
had and it gets diagnosed and you can
actually like bring it to the attention
of the player. So that's the big thing.
I mean, the hospitals are here. They
move the players around. So there's a
medical component, there's an on-field
component, there's an off-field
component, the interviews. So that's
why, you know, they set it up the way
that they do.
>> I'm going to make sure I ask this
carefully. It's not that you like
Indianapolis, but do you like the
combine being in Indianapolis?
>> Yeah, I love it. I mean, I've said I
said it in my It's just It's a great
location. The logistics work. So you
have the dome, you have the convention
center, you have the the meeting spaces,
you have all the hotels really in one
spot, so the teams can be kind of in one
spot, the hospitals are accessible. So I
mean, Jeff Foster and the national
scouting crew do a great job. Um, so I
mean, it sounds like it's going to be
here for at least another two to three
years, I think, which is great for
everybody. Hopefully it's here for the
duration. Um, but it it works. I mean,
and you know, I think it's it's a great
situation for everybody involved. Yeah,
I feel like people don't always
understand it's not a spectator event. I
know they have some fans at some point.
>> They've made it a spectator event. The
onfield compos component,
>> but it really is a working sort of
convention.
>> That's exactly what it is, Mark. You're
here to work and the way the schedule is
set up. So, like we had interviews last
night from 7 to 11. All right. During
the day, this a little bit more
opportunity to do this. You have to meet
with the media. You're going to meet
with agency representatives. And then
tonight, we're going to go from 7 to 11
again. And then tomorrow morning, we got
a group in the morning, got a group in
the afternoon. Same thing on Thursday
and the onfield work starts I think late
Thursday into Friday. So again like
that's you know that's what we're here
for.
>> Nick everybody should say everybody but
fans a lot of times are always like well
and you brought up Kamari last year
which I think is great. All the 40 time
this and the vertical leap that and the
bench press this. So many people have
talked about well it's this one event
that get that got this guy drafted. it
was this one drill or this time that got
this guy drafted and that that does end
up getting you in trouble if you end up
doing that. You've told us over the
years, no, we take the whole we take
everything into account. But I'm going
to make you Jeff Foster for a second.
All these different drills that we have.
If you could change one, if you could
change one drill or event for the
combine, what would you do?
>> I would probably start with the
offensive line. And again, like I know
everybody's run a 40 is traditional, but
that's not
>> offensive linemen are never going to be
asked to do that, right? So really
what's more applicable is kind of their
10 or their 20. So you can kind of see
how explosive, how do they move in a
short area.
>> And then the big thing with drills is
you want to try to set up as many drills
again across positions that are going to
be applicable to potentially what a
player is asked to do. So
>> certain positions a little bit easier to
do than others. So I think it's always
just kind of looking at the drills. Are
we doing the right drills? Does that
make sense? Are we doing that drill just
because we've done it or we're doing
this drill because there's an actual
application? I think those are the
things that they probably have to
continue to discuss and look at. Are we
really getting the most out of it so we
can give the best evaluation to the
players?
>> Yeah, I think the offensive linement
would appreciate not having to run a 40
because if they're running 40 yards,
they're
>> chasing somebody Dan Connley returning a
kickoff.
>> Well, that's that's a different story.
>> Exactly. Exactly. Run 10 yards, hit
somebody, run another five, and that's
pretty much it. Nick, free agency
approaching as you said, you have the
legal tampering, whatever, getting ready
to start within a couple of weeks. What
is it like getting up to that starting
line when it's okay, engines revving,
phone charged, here we go. And you have
your own free agents to be that you
might be making offers to as well.
>> No, you're balancing a lot of
information, a lot of data. And look,
the agents are here. They're going to
probably talk to every team and just try
to get a gauge of what potentially they
think the market is going to be. So we
start, okay, here's our group of
players. All right, let's make sure we
communicate with them. Whatever our
decision is going to be. Okay, got it.
All right. And then once we transition,
so we've gone through the pro scouting
department. I mean, DJ, Steve Cargle,
Nate, uh, you know, Lipford, Chris
Blanco have spent time kind of building
the free agent board. All right, so
certain positions. Okay, here's who's
available. Here's the supply. Here's the
demand. Here's our grade. And then it's
taking a group of those players, giving
them to the coaches. What's your
evaluation? and what's your vision? Is
it similar to what we see? So that's
what we've taken the last call it three
to four weeks doing so that we're
prepared and it's going to move quick.
Players are going to come off the board.
So maybe you have a group of five or
six. We say look, you know, we be
comfortable with any one of these five.
Okay, got it. Maybe one player's marks a
little bit more than you thought it was
going to be. Okay, this player actually
falls into more favorable contractual
situation. Okay, then maybe we can jump
in and capitalize. So it's going to
happen pretty quick. I mean, there's
going to get deals that are basically
done. So, at 12:01, like they're going
to be announced. Joe Smith signed with
so- and so. Yeah. So, that's And you got
to be ready. Okay, that player's off the
board. All right, let's go to the next
one.
>> Like Albert Haynesworth signing that
contract at 12:01.
>> There was no there was no tampering
before that.
>> He made that contract in one minute.
>> There's legal and there's illegal
tampering. So, there's probably a
combination of both. That's
>> Nick, we at the we were at the Senior
Bowl. Um James, you mentioned James
Liford. Libert was up for the GM job in
Atlanta and there were a number of
coaches. Uh Dino was being mentioned for
DC jobs. You know, Corey was mentioned
for DC jobs. Obviously with success
there come teams that want to pull those
guys. Keeping a lot of those guys, you
know, in they either pulled out of those
jobs for some reason or in James Casey
ended up getting the GM job. But you're
having that happen more often. How much
more prepared do you have to be for
those situations to kind of kind of
think ahead like, hey, down the road we
might lose lip, we might lose Dino, we
might lose an offensive coach. How often
and how much do you have to think ahead
with those kind of situations?
>> No, Johnny, it's definitely relevant.
So, you always have to be prepared with
contingency plans. Okay, if you it's
just no different than a player. If you
lose this player, what are options? If
you lose this coach, okay, do we have an
option internally? We have to go out.
Same thing. So I mean Demoik and I are
very proud that you know we have people
in our building that people around the
league feel have value and part of our
job and responsibility is to help and
prepare and develop those individuals as
much as possible. That's our
responsibility to everybody in the
program understanding as opportunities
come up we always want any end that
individual to do what's best for their
individual situation. We understand
that. We've all kind of been there. So,
um, you know, it's great for those folks
and I'd say by the same token, it's
great that they're still in the
building. It's only going to continue
hopefully to enhance our program and the
longer we keep them around probably the
better it is for everybody.
>> Not that you want them to leave. It's
nice that they are desired by other
teams, but your own situation, do you
say, "Hey, be patient. Your opportunity
might come. You were in the league for a
couple of decades working hard. You
finally get the opportunity and look
what you've done with it." So, is that
an example for them? Yeah, I mean I've
just try to counsel people just whatever
you're doing, just do the best job you
can with the situation that you're in.
Whatever is going to happen, some of
it's out of your control at some point.
If you have to make a decision, then you
go through your decision-m process and
figure out, you know, what makes the
most sense for for you individually. So,
um, yeah, to your point, I mean, I was
blessed and fortunate to be in a good
situation, had opportunities pop up at
different points. I mean, ultimately
didn't feel that those made sense. And
then kind of got to the end there where
this was a situation where I felt, you
know what, I'm ready for this.
Understanding going back to Johnny's
original question, probably wasn't a
great situation, but in the end, it's
what you do with it and what you make of
it. And in the end, you just focus on
just doing the best you can that
particular day, just trying to make the
most situation, kind of stacking days,
and that's all anybody can ever ask.
>> Nick, I am this question. It it came
popped up in my head and I remembered I
asked Amika this question back months
ago. What is an absolute non-negotiable
for a Texan player? Meaning you see this
in a scouting report or you see this on
the field, you know, absolutely without
a doubt, no matter what the time is, no
matter what the size is, that guy can't
be at Hast Texan.
>> Yeah. If they're just not a team first
player and don't have a selfless mindset
and a selfless mentality, it's probably
going to be hard for that player to have
success in our building. We have a lot
of humble, hardworking, selfless people
that put the team ahead of themselves.
So, to bring a player in that doesn't
have those qualities, it's probably
going to be difficult.
>> And I would say if you're a defensive
player, especially, um, physicality and
violence are non-negotiable. So, you're
either gonna play that way or you're
not. Like, it's not an option. So, I
mean, that's what we have to go through
the evaluation process and see some of
the players that have those traits and
attributes.
>> I have one more before we get to the
really important question, but we were
talking earlier about training camp and
maybe 18 game schedule down the line and
everything. And I thought, man, training
camp is a long grind, very physical.
Sometimes you lose players. Johnny said,
yeah, you have to learn how to tackle
though, get the tackling going. Is there
any other way to do that or what's the
best way to do that? You guys must have
conversations about this all the time.
How to be that physical violent team yet
not put too much wear and tear? It's got
to be a tough balance.
>> Yeah, if you watch us practice, we
practice fast and we practice with
intent and we have a certain playing
style with which we play in practice and
you want to take care of the players.
You're prioritizing their safety.
>> We typically don't tackle and bring guys
to the ground. It's not what we believe
in. Domigo doesn't believe in that. But
you can still improve as a tackler. Like
we talk a lot about just getting a body
on a body. So going getting to the ball
with pace and speed and physicality and
getting a body on a body. And then
there's certain things that you know you
can drill it, you can technique it, you
the coach can take a bag or there's
certain things you can do where you can
work the other components that you're
going to have to do on Sunday. So try to
do it in as safe an environment as
possible. Look, have we had players get
injured in practice things pop up? Yeah.
But we want try to have everybody on
their feet, but just practicing fast,
practicing physical, and practicing with
intent.
>> Okay. So, there's a contest here.
Hypothetical about like where we're
going to go like eat dinner or something
like that.
>> I don't even I don't even know where
this is going
contest.
>> What if they This is totally
hypothetical. They said, "Nick, you get
an extra The winner gets an extra third
round pick comp. The GMs have to compete
in a combine drill." What drill are you
picking?
>> Oh, boy.
>> All right. There. Is it an existing
drill or is it a drill that like
>> It's an existing drill. So you got to
pick one of the drills we're running out
here and you have to win it. So what
drill would you pick for everybody to do
where you feel like you're going to come
out on top?
>> I would like probably give myself a shot
on the gauntlet drill.
>> Like I think I have like decent hand eye
coordination and could catch it on the
move. So
>> a bunch of GMs aren't catching a ball.
So, well, I know that, but there's some
>> I might have to wear gloves, but like I
think I could go out there and
>> Did you wear gloves in college?
>> I did not. I wasn't a glove, you know,
on my throwing hand or glove on the off
hand. I was a pouch guy that had the the
hand warmers. Oh, yeah. My hands really
never got cold. I didn't have the
biggest hand. So, I just wanted to make
sure I had like a nice firm grip on
>> Was the glove technology as good? Not
even close. Cuz now some of these
gloves, it's you throw the gloves up in
the air, they catch the ball.
>> Well, they have gloves designed
specifically like for the elements. So
you actually have a little bit of
traction on the on the glove.
>> Very nice
>> gauntlet without without resorting.
>> That's my favorite drill, the gauntlet.
>> I had one more because we've talked
about your eating habits before. Very
healthy. Uh and being on the road with
the team. Hey, the team travels with the
team food. So you have that best
nutritionist in the league in that.
>> Exactly. And I know you guys infiltrate
the hotels. We could talk about that
another time and help prepare the food.
So it's the Texans way. But what about
when Nick Cacerio's traveling to
Indianapolis where it's shrimp cocktail
sauce and steaks and whatever? So, how
do you handle?
>> I stay true to form.
>> I have my my go-to, but I try to stay
disciplined with my meal. So, I try not
to branch out too far. So, I find a
place that has things that I'm going to
eat
>> and we'll make it work. Did I have
dinner last night? I think I went to
Panera last night before I did our
interviews.
>> All right.
>> Had a soup and a salad. So, I'm sure
that's not like a high priority for
>> going to Prime 47 getting Caesar without
the dressing,
>> right? No, I'm not doing that. So
>> stick, thanks a lot for joining us. Good
luck.